Software Engineering Radio episode 32
SOA 2A.
Hello everybody to another episode of
Software Engineering Radio. Um this is
the second part of our series of
episodes on Service Oriented
Architecture.
Um it is about using SOA together with
model driven development as well as
several other issues
on SOA. We also talked a little bit
about some of the technologies that are
involved with the SOA. Now um this
should have been originally one episode.
However, after recording it, we noticed
that it had taken us 90 minutes.
So we decided to uh separate the episode
into two episodes and that's why we
called it SOA 2A and the next one will
be SOA 2B. Uh we didn't call it two and
three because they're really basically
the same session just separated into
into two episodes. So this one is SOA 2A
and uh next week or in 10 days actually,
you'll hear SOA 2B.
Um it's Eberhard and myself Markus
who'll be doing this episode. Have fun.
So why are we talking about this topic?
What is the kind of
reason that you came up with it?
Well, I mean everybody's talking about
SOA, right? So I decided I had to talk
about SOA, too. And
since I really always talk about model
driven development, I had to find a way
how to talk about SOA and still talk
about model driven development.
Okay, and now seriously
Anyway, so
you know, I I I got a little bit
frustrated about some of the SOA talk
and presentations and articles and stuff
because everybody
talks about specific technologies. I
mean,
people did understand in the meantime
that SOA is not web services, but still
um SOA is considered
a topic that that can be solved with
certain technologies and and I think
that's that's really wrong. I think two
things. First of all, SOA is
has has, you know, has a relationship to
to business, business processes,
business cases, and these kinds of
things. Some of that stuff you discussed
in the SOA episode one, the one where
you explained kind of the basics of SOA.
And on the more technical side, I think
that SOA is really an architectural
paradigm, um an architectural style or
whatever. And so, I like to look at um
this topic from a really from an
architectural perspective. And if I talk
about architecture, I really like to
talk about models because models are a
way
um of capturing architectural concepts
formally and and really fixing fixing
their meaning. So, the idea of SOA
becomes more touchable or more concrete.
So, that's kind of the motivation.
Okay, but I mean, on on the other hand,
it's um
one of the problems with SOA is probably
that everybody says it's uh like the the
stuff that we always used to do, like
component uh driven development or
integration and so on. So, isn't that um
something that a danger that that um
your approach also has?
Well, I mean, the good thing about SOA
is that everybody can decide for
themselves themselves what what it
really means to them. And um because
it's not I I it's not really very
concisely defined. So, so
some people think that SOA is basically
component-based development as we've
done it or as we should have done it for
years. So,
you define component building blocks.
They have responsibilities. They have
interfaces, in this case called
services.
And they also use services that are
defined elsewhere. Other people say that
SOA is basically enterprise application
integration, EAI.
Something that's been around for a long
time. So, you basically have
asynchronous loosely coupled
message-based communications. Data
structures have to be routed, filtered,
mapped, translated between applications.
And finally, some people say, and that's
kind of what you said in the last
episode, among other things, is that
the most important part of SOA aspect is
the business process modeling aspect
where
SOA is business-driven. Every service
has to have a meaning to business and
and the the factoring of the processes
into separate artifact or aspect is kind
of central.
Now, I think that probably all of these
views are correct or or a part of what
SOA really is. And at least all of these
are problems in complex enterprise
systems.
And that's actually something that I
agree to. And
there was also a comment on the last
episode that basically stated that it
was somehow focused on the
externalization of business processes.
And I'm not really sure whether the is
the case. So, basically I I agree that
from the technical side it's somehow
somewhere in between those things.
Yeah.
However, it's
it's the business-driven
approach that is probably new to
Yeah, it's it's it's business that
drives all that stuff.
Yeah.
So, that's the the the raison d'être or
the something like that.
Try some French. So, and and that's why
I also think that the three views of
what SOA means which I adjust this
described are actually fit together
quite nicely because as the foundation
of an SOA you typically have a really
well-defined component-based
architecture.
At the end of this episode we'll talk
about SCA, the new standard service
component architecture and they do
exactly that. On top of that you can
then basically
orchestrate business processes and then
using legacy adapter components or
mapper or filter components you can
actually do the EAI stuff. So I don't
think that the three views are kind of
contradictory. They they fit together
nicely. It's just that everybody has
their own, you know, thinks some of one
one particular one of these three
alternatives is most important.
Because it's a product vendor in that
very space. Yeah.
For example.
So and then there there are two other
things that are important for SOA and
they have also been around for quite a
long time and that is the separation
between technical and business concerns,
right? The idea that service interfaces
only expose business operations or or
that that the data that goes, you know,
between services is business data,
whatever that means.
So the idea is to factor out technical
concerns like security, persistence or
failover. Now, I mean application
servers have done that all the time so
that's nothing really new, but it's
still important. And also manageability.
You want to be able to monitor your
services. You want to know which of the
components are you know, have which
level of load
to be able to manage things and and and
also consider or take care about um
service levels so you can actually
guarantee some kind of performance. So
so maybe to summarize, I think if you
talk about SOA, you have to talk about
component-based architecture as a
foundation for the SOA on top of it.
And actually it's not surprising that
those topics
appear over and over again because for
example of
of concerns
is originally brought into play by
Dijkstra. So, it's and it's quite an old
guy.
So, therefore
it's probably the the ghost that is
going to hunt us for quite a while.
So, maybe let's let's talk about a
couple of additional requirements
for SOAs or for for complex and big
systems in general.
One is I think you need to keep things
technology independent. You must be able
to migrate the infrastructure to
tomorrow's new hype technology. So, you
have to make sure that the
implementation of your business services
and also, you know, the description of
workflows and processes and and all that
stuff is really technology independent.
The other challenge that I really think
is crucial is that things remain
testable. If If whenever you want to
test the
a service
you know, it's it's functionality like
add two numbers in the trip most trivial
case, you don't want to do a remote call
using all kinds of enterprise service
bus things. So, you really need to be
sure that you can factor out the
infrastructure and keep the application
logic testable.
Actually, you cannot stress the
technology independence enough because
if you want to build enterprise
applications, you're facing
applications that run for decades
and you can surely not do every
technology shift in those decades by
migrating some code or doing things like
that. You have to be somehow stable and
if you look at Java for example, there
are just so many new technologies that
it's really crucial to be
technology independent and have an easy
way to
update
your environment while not changing the
business logic.
Yeah, and you can even
um take this one step further. I would
say that probably the
the biggest problem today when migrating
legacy systems is that legacy systems
are typically built in a way where the
different aspects or concerns of the
application are not separated nicely,
right? So, you if you if you take a
piece of COBOL code or or whatever Java
code for that matter that mixes
technical concerns that somehow, you
know, the where the process the business
process is hidden somewhere in in in the
in in in the implementation of whatever
artifact, then it's really impossible to
extract the aspects and reuse them. So,
when talking about enterprise systems
and SOA in particular, it's important
that the various aspects of the systems,
service descriptions, communication
protocols, um processes,
whatever, that they are described in a
in a clear and and, you know, in a clean
manner that is not uh
polluted by other aspects. And that's
where models come in.
But, um
before we look at models, um I really
want to to stress two other things. I've
I've been on several SOA projects, big
one that I probably shouldn't mention
the organization in particular. And so,
there are other requirements that I
think are really crucial for SOA. One is
that um you the the usually
an SOA is something where the the whole
enterprise is involved. So, you have
many, many parties that want to be or
have to be involved with this thing. And
they have to be able to communicate
effectively. So, you need a well-defined
set of terms and concepts that you want
to talk about when designing your your
SOA. And also, you need to you you need
to stay agile
um with respect to changes. I've seen
systems where when you added a new
attribute to some data structure, it
took a week until um this this change
propagated through all the generated and
configured and deployed other artifacts.
So, that's you know, nobody's going to
change anything in such a
in such an environment.
And finally, um you have to consider
organizational aspects. Like for
example, if the SOA initiative is driven
by some central IT department who wants
to standardize their middleware, then
the application you know, the
application development departments
probably don't care about that. If for
them introduction of SOA makes things
more complicated, they will sabotage it.
They will not They will not You know,
they will not collaborate. So, you have
to make sure that everybody's There is
something for everybody in when you
introduce an SOA.
Yeah, which basically means that um the
the real problem of uh introducing an
SOA is probably on the level of uh the
organization and um
the management and the business backing
and things like that, which is something
that is probably uh important for for
every kind of IT systems, but because uh
SOA is such a is typically such a
large-scale and interferes with so many
systems and so on, it's especially
important in that area.
Yeah. And also even if the if you know,
if the business and and your your your
boss and the CEO and everybody really
wants to do it, there are still a lot of
technical challenges. So, yes, I agree
that you need to have the business
things, you know, right, and everybody
needs to support it, but still if you
have all that, there is still a lot of
technical things to to to discuss. So,
it's still worth talking about the
technical aspects of an SOA even if you
say that the business is kind of the
most important driver.
Yeah, absolutely. I mean, my my general
uh approach is nowadays to say that
technology cannot uh save a project.
However, it can um make it fail.
Yes. And that's why it's important.
Yeah.
Okay, then let's take a closer look at
the role of models here, right?
So, I think abstraction is key and when
you define an SOA
and so it's really essential that you
define meta models and domain specific
languages then
that actually describe the architectural
the architectural concepts. You could I
mean if you're an MDA person, you would
probably call this an architecture PIN,
right? It's a a platform independent
model that doesn't describe any business
concepts but rather one that describes
the building blocks of your SOA such as
services, components, quality of service
constraints, deployment information and
so on. And again, this
this model has to be independent of the
concrete deployment platform. You want
to map this at a later stage to web
services, JBI, SCA, whatever. for the
traditional folks. And of course then if
you map these conceptual things once
they're nicely defined and once you
define a programming model, once you
want to map these to implementation
technologies, then it's obviously a good
idea to automate this this mapping and
that's where the model driven
development and code generation
aspect comes in.
Yeah, however, one thing that I'm
wondering is
um
especially with a POJO based programming
models,
the code itself is already independent
of the concrete deployment platform.
Yes.
So,
why is there still use for doing it with
models instead of POJOs?
Well, first of all, I agree that POJOs
with a couple of annotations
can be a good starting point and they
are
usually if it if done right independent
of the deployment technology and of of
middleware.
However,
in the end, what what these POJOs do
of there I mean, if you define classes
using POJOs that implement services,
then you can only describe one of
several viewpoints that you need to
describe in order to describe a
SOA-based system. So, even if you use um
POJOs to describe or to implement
services and basically to implement
components, there are still many other
things you'd have to describe for an SOA
that that cannot be, you know, that
cannot be kind of welded into classes
and then annotated with annotations or
some something. So, there is other stuff
and I'll I'll go into that in a moment.
If If we have If you want to be able to
draw a model of the architecture, then
of course, we need a metamodel that
defines the words, the language elements
that we can use in order to describe our
architecture. And And these language
elements that the the grammar for the
language with with which we describe the
architecture, that's the metamodel. Um
So, and and to come back
Sounds easy.
It sounds easy.
Okay. It is.
Okay. To So, I I mentioned before that
um there are various layers that we
probably want to describe. The lowest
layer being component services
deployment, the next layer uh business
processes, and then some other layer
with external services, and maybe uh
legacy adapters or something. And in my
view, to be able to describe the lowest
layer, this component service layer of
an SOA, you need at least three
viewpoints. Viewpoints are
models that describe certain aspect or a
certain view of the architecture. One is
the type model that describes services,
their interfaces, data structures,
components, and which services these
components provide, and at least as
importantly and often neglected, the
services which these components use. If
you don't have that in your model, you
you only know who provides what, but you
don't know who uses what, so you can't
have any real dependency tracking.
So, and that is the kind of model that
you can describe with classes and
annotations, POJOs.
The next kind of model is the
composition model, and that describes
logical instances of uh those components
and how they're wired. That means if I
have a a component uh address manager
that provides some address query service
and I have another component, the
customer manager, which requires a
reference to an address query service,
then on the instance level, where I have
an instance of the address manager and
an instance of the customer manager, I
need to connect those two, right? I have
to connect connect the the required
reference from the customer manager to
the address manager. This is the
instance and composition model.
And note that this is still independent
of any specific deployment and
technology. It doesn't say on which of
your 5,000 servers a particular instance
runs and, you know, how big the pool
size is and what middleware you use and
which implementation technology. It's
just a logical composition. And then the
final model, the third viewpoint, is
then actually the deployment model that
maps your
instances to technology and also um to
machines or processes or what other
applications servers.
Um you agree to that point?
Yeah, I mean, basically what you're
saying is that um
it's still a component driven approach.
Yes.
We need to define which components there
are and how they're implemented.
Yes.
Uh we need to have a model that
describes how those components interact
and where they should be deployed.
how the instances interact. That's
really important. If you have, for
example, in in my my project I was
recently, they had, for example, the the
component it was actually really called
customer manager, and they had one in
Germany, they had one in Austria, and
they had one in Czech Republic, I guess.
And so, there were it was the same
component, but it was instantiated three
times in different
in this case countries. So, you really
had to distinguish these different
component instances when when wiring
them because if the German call center
would happen to access the Czech um
customer database, that's not very
useful.
Yeah, it might be fun, but not really
useful. Yeah.
Yeah. So, the the meta models for these
um
for these
models are are I mean, it's really hard
to describe you know, meta models or
graphs. So, it's a bit tough to describe
them in an audible audio-only form. But,
the type meta model contains, as I said,
components, ports, services, maybe a
definition of how the service expects
interactions like, you know, send me
this message and then within 5 seconds
I'll reply either with this reply
message or with that error message,
right? And then, of course, you have to
define the data structures that the
services use. You will often in this
case you would use a XML schema. Yes,
it's not tech not technology
independent, but it's so ubiquitous that
is a it's acceptable to to bind yourself
to the technology there.
So, I mean, basically but basically this
is like WSDL
Yeah.
or IDL and things like that. It's
It's on the same conceptual level.
Yes, absolutely. It Yes, yes. I mean, um
the the problem with WSDL in one in its
1.x anchor incarnation is that, first of
all, it doesn't really define the notion
of a component
and also it doesn't really define any,
you know, um re
you know, non-trivial protocols. Like,
for example, you could associate a
protocol state machine with a service
definition. That's how the embedded
folks do it. Why not do it the same way?
In WSDL 2.x, things are getting better.
There is the notion of a component and
you can define which services a
component provide and also which
services a component uses. So, WSDL 2.x
is really much closer to what I'd like
to see. WSDL 1.X only provides, you
know, only describes a service from the
provider's point of view, and that's
absolutely not sufficient to describe a
system.
Okay. Yeah, my
my point was to to
to provide an analogy to to relate to
the grasp of
the concept.
Yeah, but I mean, still worthwhile to
talk about the differences.
Yeah, absolutely.
And and then, as we said before, this
composition meta model contains
component instances, which are obviously
instances of component types defined in
the previous meta model,
and then the wires between the
components, so that's all Sorry, between
the component instances.
And then finally, the deployment model
contains meta model contains concepts
like system, node, container. And of
course, if you do it right, then you can
if you if you say, you know, you have
this node like server XYZ, and on this
runs a J2EE container, and you deploy an
instance to this
um container, then your generator can
derive from that which kind of glue code
it has to generate in order to have your
POJO implementation of the service run
on the particular infrastructure. So,
that's actually really neat. You can
derive a lot of interesting information
from from from that
uh from these three viewpoints. And of
course, you can vary all of these three
viewpoints separately. That's actually
why we have three different models, one
for each viewpoint. You can take the
same logical composition
uh model and deploy it on different
yeah, uh infrastructures. One
infrastructure is typically everything
in one process running on top of Spring,
for example, for unit testing. And
another infrastructure could be the
highly distributed, scalable J2EE,
whatever system, and I'm not implying
that Spring is not scalable, um where
which is your production environment.
You don't have to change your
composition model or your component
implementation. It's just deployed on a
different infrastructure, different glue
code is generated, and and that's it.
In the case of Spring, there there
wouldn't even be glue code generated,
but it would rather be a different
Spring
Spring configuration.
Yeah.
But
it's still the same thing. So, you would
basically generate something that says,
"Please talk to this server over HTTP."
While for the unit test, you will
probably have everything local running
local on one node.
Another thing that that just crossed my
mind, um this is very much like
the new Visual Studio stuff.
Yeah.
Um so so do you want to talk about that
or
I mean, first of all, I mean, as I said,
I
I haven't invented all the stuff I'm
talking about. So, there are several
other initiatives that think think in
that direction. SCA is one thing, and
also then this I mean, in Visual Studio,
whatever, I think 2005, Microsoft has
built a set of modeling tools based on
the Microsoft DSL tools, you know,
software factories and stuff, where you
I think they're called Enterprise
Designer or something, where you can
actually really graphically deploy and
and you you know, your your services
onto your hardware.
So, yes, it's the same idea.
Okay.
But not using UML, but
Yeah, I mean, I'm not talking about
using UML, either.
Okay.
I mean, you can you you use UML if you
want to, but you you have to I mean, you
have to come up with some kind of
notation. It can be a textual notation.
You can build your own textual DSL to to
to to describe these things. It's quite
nice because that makes diffs and merges
based on CVS much easier than if you
have graphical models. But that's a
different topic.
So, one last comment on these on these
things,
I talked about defining the connections
between component instances in this
composition model. And that sounds like
that you that sounds like that sounds as
if you'd have to define all those
connections statically when you model
your system and then there would be no
dynamics in the system at all.
Yes, that's one way of building an SOA.
However, there is no problem in adding
dynamics by saying, "Okay, instead of
wiring two component instances directly,
the alternative would be that you you
just specify in your model which
information should be used at runtime to
find the target of your wire or of your
connector, you know, based on some
registry or naming service or UDDI or
whatever. And so then you can have still
formally you still have a static you
know, you still draw a line between two
component instances, but the line
actually doesn't really point to another
instance. It basically points into
nowhere and the line, the connector has
a number of criteria by which at runtime
it will find a suitable subcomponent
instance. That's also very old concept.
In CORBA it was called trader.
In Spring it's called auto wiring.
Right.
And not really because I thought auto
wiring basically gets you some arbitrary
instance based on type equality
equality.
And that's not what I'm talking about. I
really think you you should still
describe additional properties like you
need a component with this service level
or a component instance with this this
service level, you know, located in that
country or whatever.
Can you give an example where this is
really useful?
The the scenario is as follows. If you
have
again, you know, this customer manager
thing. We said we have two customer
managers or three, one for Germany, one
for Austria, one for Czech Republic.
Now, if you are the German call center
component thing, then you have to talk
to a to you know, a component instance
that provides the customer manager
interface and that manages the German
customers.
Okay? So one of the criteria for the
lookup would be I need one that manages
German customers. So what you could do
is in this in this basically in this
query to your trader service, you could
say give me a component instance which
provides the customer manager interface,
which manages German customer. So, that
would be a property, you know, country
equals Germany. And there might still be
five or six instances of that component
running in different cities in Germany
or redundantly in some in some computing
center. So, there is still some dynamics
in there. But it it it's still
you know, it's a it's it's a look-up
based on properties and that's what
traders do.
And the real advantage is if I add
another system for say France
No, that that won't change anything
because I I won't find that because I
query with country equals Germany. But
if I add another machine in my in my in
my in my computing center or another
computing center in another town, I
would then, you know, load balancing
fail over wise, I would then maybe find
the other component instance that
satisfies my query.
But that that's just another layer for
doing load balancing, which you can do
on
a lot of different layers. So,
I I mean
I got the impression that the real
advantage is that my system can easily
integrate additional
uh yes, countries for example.
Yeah, that that's another thing, but
that would also require that the
configuration data in that connector can
actually be changed at run time. So, The
the only point I I want to make is that
although it sounds like a completely
static configuration,
it's not the case. It's very easy to
adapt this to dynamic scenarios if you
need to. That's my whole point.
So, um
let's take a concrete example like the
customer service you you mentioned and
uh see how this is actually taken into
real life and real code.
Right.
So, what do I do first to get this thing
running?
So, first what you have to do is you
have to define the types you work with.
These are the service interfaces, your
data structures, and the components
which describe which provide or require
interfaces.
So,
taking the example of a customer service
that we've been talking already about,
how do I actually get this to
do something useful, to get it running
on some machines?
Right. So, I start by defining an
interface, for example, I customer query
that contains an operation get customer
data, and you pass in some query
parameters like, for example, the I
don't know, the name of the customer or
whatever.
And then you define a component. It
could be called customer manager, which
provides this interface we just defined,
and maybe that requires an interface
database manager in order to access the
database. As I said, it's really
important that you don't just define
what a component provides, but also what
it requires, you know, to to close your
dependency graph. So, you have to model
that in some way, and how you model that
depends on what you decided you want to
model with. This can be UML, it can be a
textual modeling language.
I mean, that's that's now a really
technical tooling problem that we
probably shouldn't cover in this
episode. That's just MDSD stuff.
Yeah, but that's where the meta meta
model comes in. So, the meta model
decides whether you do it with
boxes and lines, or whether you write it
down in some visual way, and what you
no. Not at all. Not at all.
Not at all. The meta model defines I'm
good that you asked that. The meta model
defines what concepts are available,
interface, component, the fact that a
component can provide an interface, and
so on. The concrete syntax for your
domain specific language, that is that
is what defines the you know, the visual
appearance, whether it's going to be
text or graphics. So, that's really kind
of orthogonal. You can have several
concrete syntaxes for the same meta
model.
So, is that kind of like the general
universal meta model for this kind of
applications that we are talking about?
I mean, there are a couple of best
practices.
I've I've captured some of them in some
of my my my my papers and patterns, and
then of course there are some meta
models defined as part of for example
the SCA standard. Also WSDL 2.0 has a
reasonable meta model. So, there are
various places where you can go and and
get inspiration from. However, and
really great you ask.
Um it's the point is I wouldn't I really
wouldn't go and you know get something
from somewhere and buy a tool that does
all that for you.
You know, this is where you define your
architecture. This is the master plan
for your systems. Do this yourself.
Inspire yourself, get ideas from others.
Don't you know don't reinvent the wheel,
but don't just you know download
something and you know use a tool. This
is the master description for your world
for your IT world. You really should do
that yourself. It's going to bite you if
you if you just you know follow some
vendor and do something. Yes, if you
know you're going to use SCA then you
know take a look at their meta model and
don't invent things that are completely
different, but keep that to yourself.
Okay.
So
So basically you are saying that it's
you should still do it yourself because
the standardized
There is no official standard.
Yeah, because it's
It basically defines your architecture
because the the
architecture is different for each and
every application. It's more useful to
do it yourself than to buy it off the
shelf.
Yeah, I mean you know there is a lot of
there is still a lot of stuff to buy off
the shelf. All the middleware, the
enterprise service buses, compilers,
IDEs, monitoring tools. You know, there
is still a lot of stuff you can buy, but
this is the master from which all of the
other systems are populated or otherwise
you know you know
a generate you you you generate
configuration files and all that. And
and and since this is really the master,
you really must make sure that it's
under your control.
Okay, but let's get back to how we
implement that stuff. Now, once you, you
know, once you model your your the the
structure of your your your system,
components, interfaces, services, you
can now generate, for example, an
implementation skeleton. Could be a Java
class
which, you know, contains a couple of
infrastructural things like, for
example, the provisioning of the
interface and and other things.
And um you extend from that class and
you implement the business methods
manually, for example. So, at this time
we don't at this point we don't, you
know, consider implementing the service
as something we want to do in a
model-driven way. The model-driven stuff
is just the the technical
infrastructure.
What do I do when I want to integrate
some legacy system?
Can we defer this question or can you
ask it again later? I mean, I I kind of
would like to go through this thing once
and then we can discuss discuss this
later. I think I even we have it on our
on our plan anyway.
Okay. Okay.
Okay, so um and now once you defined uh
the implementation for your component
or you actually you didn't define it,
you you programmed it, right? Following
some some some some some some
restrictions provided by the code
generator and constraints and stuff.
Then you would you then you're able to
define a composition model as well as a
deployment model and you can actually
already run the system.
Assuming you have the generator that
generates all the the the the glue code
that maps the implementation or the
POJOs onto your whatever infrastructure,
right?
So,
before we go on with the next kind of
topics, I really would like to discuss
an additional aspect which is
asynchronous communication.
I we we kind of assumed implicitly while
in the previous discussion that we have
this kind of remote procedure call thing
that a service invokes procedures
defined by another service or a
component actually invokes operations
defined by another component. That is
just one implementation alternative. So,
there are actually three ways you can do
this. One is you can define operations
as we just said, and basically implement
them invoke them synchronously. Just a
remote procedure call.
The second way you can do it is you can
define how you know, if if component A
requires an interface provided by some
other component, then you can define as
part of this requirement
whether the other interface should be
talked to synchronously or
asynchronously. And if you for example
say that your customer manager wants to
talk to the address manager
asynchronously, then the the the
interface that you as the customer
manager see, the Java interface that's
generated particularly for you has an
asynchronous
yeah, notion. So, you you would have
like instead of calling an operation you
get the return value, you'd get in as a
alternatively you'd get a future, you
know, just future pattern which is
basically an object on which you can
poll the return value as you want
when and if you want to poll it. So,
depending on how you want to communicate
with your peer component, you just mark
that up in your model, and the generator
generates the necessary API and all the
middleware configuration so that you can
actually communicate asynchronously.
And the third implementation alternative
is that you don't really define
services as containing operations, but
rather the service interface is just
contain messages. So, you would
basically define a message oriented
interface. So,
so we we can discuss what which is
better and you know, which is more
loosely coupled and which is more
service oriented.
You know, the kind of the community kind
of gravitates towards the message
oriented view, but that doesn't change
the the picture. It's just that the
interface is not defined as a set of
operations you call, but rather as a set
of messages that your component or the
provider of the interfaces can
understand. And usually you also define
a protocol that says which messages go
in and which are the replies and how
these replies are associated and related
to
the the requests.
And I mean message oriented middleware
is really strong.
Yes.
And and is probably driving most of the
larger enterprise systems. So,
it's important to bear in mind
that not everything is done by remote
procedure calls.
Right, it's just that the boundaries
between those different approaches are
really blurred. Because for example, if
you have
this, you know, this this message
oriented interface, you can still
generate an API for your clients that
basically looks like void methods and
you get callbacks
for the reply message. And that is from
an API point of view, it's
indistinguishable from asynchronously
called operations. Okay? So, it's really
important to distinguish the API and the
programming model from the underlying uh
metaphor and and also the middleware.
Okay. Um so, where does this get us? It
get us It gets us to the point where we
can implement components, service
providers, and service users without a
technology dependency, without
deployment information, without knowing
with whom which with with which other
instances they really
interact and without knowing on which
platform they will run.
But it's just a description, right? It's
not the actual code that
It's also the actual code. We have
already implemented the POJOs by
deriving or extending from the generated
skeleton class that we generated from
the type viewpoint model.
Okay, but okay, but but the model itself
just generates the skeleton, not the
implementation itself.
Absolutely. We We
Later in in the discussion we'll we'll
consider also generating the some of the
of the implement or particular kinds of
implementations.
Now that we have all that in place,
so that's basically the fundamentals. I
think we should talk about a couple of
issues in the context of SOAs, right?
For example, data ownership.
If I define a service and also define
its interface and components and all
that stuff. And if I want to interact
with somebody else, then we have to
agree on data structures. If I send you
a customer with a certain structure data
structure and you don't know this data
structure, you can't work with this
customer data, right?
Also historically people have talked you
know about the business object model. So
there was this big big object model that
contains all the data
structures you know and you need in your
business. And that's of course a really
big problem because
this was kind of the the bottleneck with
regards to changing stuff. Once you
in case you ever agreed on something,
you weren't able to change it ever again
because if everybody uses it and you
change it again, everybody else you know
has a problem. So this this is something
that historically didn't really work.
The other approach in SOAs that's
sometimes taken is that you say that
data structures are strictly local to a
service. So if I
define a customer data structure then
this data structure can only be used by
my service clients and they can't
publish it again. So that means of
course that if you have central if you
have data structures that you use all
throughout your your enterprise, then
you have to probably
you have several formal definitions of
the same logical concept. That's also a
problem.
Are you sure about that? Because
my impression is that sticking to the
customer example, everybody in the
company has a different view on the
customer. So, the one is interested in
its it's his address cuz you want to
ship something to him.
Yes.
And somebody else is interested in his
telephone number or email because they
want to do some some marketing stuff
with him.
And therefore the question is whether
this
central business object model really
makes sense, right?
I Yeah, I think these are two aspects.
There are certainly some data structures
that everybody agrees upon, but or or
conceptually agrees upon. On the other
hand, you're absolutely right that
usually data is viewed with different
properties
um from from, you know, in different
departments.
I think we'll cover this aspect later.
So, that's just a different thing.
Oh, and the the other thing that I'm
wondering about is
if you do have this centralized object
model,
it's still probably not worth it because
uh it doesn't take into account the
requirements of the specific
applications,
which therefore might even
So, I mean, a client is probably
interested in displaying the data in a
certain way, while a back-end system is
probably interested in operating the
data in a certain way that is different
and has different requirements in terms
of how the object model should ideally
look in terms of making the the
development easy and also making the
stuff performant.
What you talk about is a kind of
controlled variability in data
descriptions. If I want a customer, then
I just need certain aspects or
attributes, and you don't need these,
right? So, this is something different.
The point I was going to make is that
there is a there is a middle ground
between, you know, having the big uh
business object model which doesn't
work, and the strictly local service
defini-
strict locality of data to a service.
And that is basically that you add
another concept in your models, and
that's, you know, you could you could
call it like domain or subsystem or
whatever, which bundles a set of
components, services, and their data
types. And then you can associate
components with this domain, then you
know there is a dependency, but uh you
don't make the dependencies global. So,
you have a way of of controlling kind of
the spread of your data type. And again,
this is something that you can easily do
if you have models, because you just add
this concept of a domain, and it it
collects a number of components, and you
can easily control all your data type
problems.
So, in that case I need to Yeah, I need
to have the the data types in the
component model as well. And basically,
I need the model of the whole IT
infrastructure of the company.
Yeah, you you you define things like
departments or domains which say, you
know, there is the domain
customer-related stuff which contains
the following seven components of these
four departments, and they have agreed
on a certain data structure. But anybody
outside this domain cannot access this
data structure, so the dependencies on
this data structure are not going to,
you know, spread widely all through your
enterprise.
And
the the interesting part is that the
model is global to the whole IT system
of the company.
Yeah, that's again another thing,
whether you want to have a global model
which everybody changes or whether there
is a more distributed development style.
That's something we'll talk about later,
but that's a related but different
aspect.
Okay.
Okay, let's let's talk about typing a
little bit. If you consider CORBA, then
the data structures are defined, you
know, using CORBA structs in your IDL
files. And then you generate from that,
you know, these interpreters basically
that um
parses the binary data and and build the
C or Java or C++ or whatever data
structures.
That is, of course, still something you
can do in the context of a SOA, no
problem with that. It's probably more
efficient than anything else. However,
there is one problem, and that is
versioning and um
compatibility. Um for example, in CORBA,
what usually happens if the two parties,
client and server, don't have the exact
same definition of a data structure,
basically the parser fails, throws an
exception, says, "You know, I don't
understand this." And that's of course a
problem if you have a big distributed
enterprise and you want to keep things
agile. And in that case, it is really
useful to interpret the data structure.
And the primary means of describing data
structures that will be interpreted is
XML. And that is where why why using XML
as data structures is actually an
advantage over binary implementations
as,
you know, typically done in CORBA. It's
not because it's human readable or all
that crap. XML is not human readable
once it gets, you know, sufficiently
complicated schema-wise. The point is
that a parser that reads the XML can
easily
skip attributes or elements it doesn't
know. It can also add default values.
You can even, you know, tweak your
interpreter to, you know, if if you
receive data that is an old version,
then you can kind of magically update
it. It's something which might be work
to do. It might be tedious, but it the
the parser won't just fail. So, that's a
bit more robust.
So, um the So, it is a good thing if you
have data structures that are not
strongly typed in the sense that your
your your generated or compiled code
depends on its particular structure, but
rather it should be interpreted.
However, there's one really important
thing you have to keep in mind. I'm not
suggesting that you shouldn't clearly
define your data and then, you know,
just, you know, you have this method, do
it, you pass in a string, right? That's
nonsense because then you have no type
information anywhere, not even in the
models. So, what I'm saying is you
should clearly define your types, for
example, is XML schema or UML or
anything else. And the two end points of
your communication should be able to
determine which version of your data
they're talking to or they're they're
receiving. They should parse it types in
a type safe manner. But all the
intermediate structures, all the you
know, brokers, all the middleware, all
the monitoring stuff, they should not
depend on the specific data structure.
They should only interpret it. And
therefore, you can easily change a data
structure without having to regenerate
and redeploy and all that of the
complete intermediate technical
infrastructure. That's kind of
important.
But you would still redeploy each and
every client and server that uh
Yeah.
on the data structure.
That that kind of depends. If I as a
service provider
add additional attributes, for example,
to my customer, then I do this because I
expect that my clients are interested in
that data additional data structure,
okay? So, if they're interested in that
new data
attribute, they obviously have to be
have to change their implementation and
they have to be redeployed, okay? But if
there are three other clients which are
not interested in that particular
attribute, they shouldn't have to care.
So, I only should have to redeploy those
um par- participants of the you know,
members of the domain to speak in the
terms of the previous kind of discussion
um that are really interested in this
change and the others shouldn't stumble
about the changed data um just because
of technical reason reasons.
Okay, so what you're saying is not just
the technical infrastructure, but also
the the clients should be stable towards
um
changes in the data model.
Yeah. Ideally, yes. I mean, again, it it
it it really I mean, it we were getting
into semantics here. If, for example,
there is a new additional attribute um
for my customer and I really want to
make sure that
all my clients take care of this
attribute. For example,
you know, is allowed to get credit. This
is a kind of semantic information that I
want everybody to consider.
Then I maybe don't want the clients to,
you know, just skip the attributes if
they don't care. So maybe there you have
to introduce the concept of changes that
are, you know, that are optional for
clients to understand and changes that
are required.
And so again, if you do it model based,
it's easy to do this because you can
mark up all these things in your models,
okay?
Yeah, the model that you described
before only models dependencies on the
level of data structures, while
in the case that you're explaining now,
you need to model dependencies on the
attributes of the data structure.
really because what you do is you would
just simply version things, right? And
you would say this new version of the
data structure is one that is compatible
to the old one, so the old clients
should continue working. And the other
next version is one that is semantically
incompatible, so the clients shouldn't
just skip over. And then there would be
some logic in the clients, which would
be generic that says if the client has
been built with version X and now comes
version X plus one and plus one is is
semantically compatible, then try to
skip all the stuff. I don't know. If
it's incompatible, throw an exception
saying hey, you're outdated.
Yeah, but which could lead to the
situation that you can hardly update
your system.
Yes, but the point is that you would, of
course, try to minimize use of those
required changes. You know, you have you
can now deliberately decide what you
want to do. If you have the compiled
interpreters like CORBA, then things are
just going to crash.
And it's, I mean, in in some cases it's
really an advantage. There are some
projects like
that that for example try to change the
customer number from six digits to eight
or stuff like that. And those projects
are probably the hardest to do in a
company because each and everyone relies
on the fact that it that the customer
number is six six digits. It's almost
like a small Y2K problem.
Yes.
That's a good comparison.
Okay, so here is where we break for
today.
Um so our 2B will be there in 10 days.
See you there and thanks for listening.
Thanks for listening to Software
Engineering Radio. If you want to get
more information about Software
Engineering Radio or if you want to give
us feedback, please go to our website at
SE-Radio.net.
You can also contact the team at
team@se-radio.net.
Although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think. Software
Engineering Radio wants to thank Henning
Pauli for the intro and outro music as
well as Loop Sun for providing the
bandwidth.
This episode of SE Radio as well as all
other episodes is licensed under
Creative Commons License. See the
Software Engineering Radio website for
details.